<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Modest enquiry concerning the election of the sheriffs of London and the right of chusing demonstrated to belong unto and to have been always adjusted to reside in the Lord Mayor, the Court of Aldermen, and the Common-Hall</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51094</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13644689</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100901</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240859708</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17026</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13644689</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 795:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Modest enquiry concerning the election of the sheriffs of London and the right of chusing demonstrated to belong unto and to have been always adjusted to reside in the Lord Mayor, the Court of Aldermen, and the Common-Hall</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mead,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sheriffs --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Crime --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Criminals --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100901:1"/>
            <p>A MODEST ENQUIRY CONCERNING THE ELECTION OF THE Sheriffs of London. AND THE <hi>RIGHT of CHƲSING</hi> DEMONSTRATED To belong unto, and to have been always adjudged to reside in the LORD MAYOR, THE COURT of ALDERMEN, AND THE Common-Hall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Mead.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100901:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100901:2"/>
            <head>A Modest Enquiry concerning the Election of the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WERE I to consult my own peace and personal safety, I should rather be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented silently to bewail the doleful and threatning posture of affairs, than take upon me to represent the condition which the rash Counsels of a few shallow, criminal, and desperate persons have reduced an excellent Prince and this flourishing Kingdom into. And were it not for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my duty to my Religion, King and Countrey, I should not so far expose and lay my self obnoxious, as I foresee I shall do at this unhappy juncture, when the passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prejudices of a certain peevish little sort of men, and their espousal of persons and interests altogether irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable with the preservation of Protestancy, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King, and the prosperity of his people, have rendred them unattentive unto, and obstinate against what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is discoursed for the allaying our unnatural heats, and the retrieving that desirable correspondence betwixt his Majesty and his subjects, which may cause him still to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversally beloved, and render him more glorious, and these Nations more prosperous and happy than ever. In what a short time have the unadvised and giddy Counsels of Five or Six unfortunate pretenders to Policy, brought the King from being the Supreme Arbitrator of all the weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100901:3"/>of <hi>Europe,</hi> and from being able to turn the scales as he pleased in this Western part of the World, into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of being hardly able to preserve peace in his own Dominions, or compose differences, and quiet animosities among his natural subjects and Liege people? And in how few years have the present Ministers reduced these renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kingdoms from being the comfort and support of our Friends, the dread and terror of our Enemies, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects either of the envy or emulation of the World, into a condition of becoming pitied of those that love us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by them that hate us, and ready (if we do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the malice of our Foes by falling upon one another) to be a prey to any that from envy, revenge, or ambition, shall entertain a design of attacking us? Who that hath not abandon'd and forfeited the reason of a man, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and abjured his love both to his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, can so much as imagine that the Methods which have been lately pursued, are either wisely adapted to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent state of things abroad, or seasonably calculated for the condition that matters are in at home?</p>
            <p>Do not all men observe a War commencing on the other side the water, wherein we cannot avoid becoming inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ested in favour of one party or another; and yet in the mean time are not divisions and rancours industriously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted and enflamed towards the weakning and disabling the Kingdom for any great or Martial undertaking? And are not all things likewise managed towards the encreasing such jealousies between the King and the generality of his people, and for the begetting that dislike in his Majesty of Parliaments, and such distrust in them of him, should ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity enforce the Assembling one, that there is little hope while matters continue to run in the present channel, either of his Majesties being in a capacity of declaring for one or the other of the contending and rival States and Princes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100901:3"/>abroad, or being able honourably to comply with the terms of those Alliances wherein he is already engaged, much less of being in a condition to answer what will be desired and expected from him upon new Treaties and Stipulations. For as nothing is more obvious than it will be impossible for us to to preserve a Neutrality, should the Foreign War proceed; seeing the Confederates are not only sensible of the Inconveniences which befel them in the last War, by the Neutrality of his Majesty, but are now less apprehensive than they were then, of any great Mischief likely to ensue towards them by our declaring against them; so that we are rationally to expect, that if they cannot obtain us to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark with them, they will look upon us as their Enemies, and treat us accordingly.</p>
            <p>And tho we ought always to believe, That whensoever the King finds how he cannot escape being imbroiled and engaged in the present War, but he will, as a wise Prince, both so far understand his Interest, and be ready to gratifie the Desires, and ardent Wishes of his People, as to joyn with the Confederates: yet as that will lead him to call a Parliament, for which some will, <hi>hostibus &amp; bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo gratiam habere,</hi> think themselves obliged to out-landish Troubles; so it is to be hop'd, That seeing those about His Majesty have wholly left off thinking, or do only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoughts to divert and adjourn their own ruine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great regard, by what appears, to the Kings Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Safety, that he will at last judg it matter worthy of his own serious consideration, whether he can reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably promise himself a happy meeting with his Parliament, or success in what he will have to propose unto them, if upon their coming together, they find things going in the Current which they have run in for some time past. Will Noble and Generous Persons, and such as represent a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant and free People, believe they should act prudently,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100901:4"/>and as men that expect to be honoured and justified by those who depute them, in shewing themselves inclined to be liberal of their own, and the Nations Money, until they have enquired, how Parliaments have come to be debased and <hi>ridiculed,</hi> and how the zealousest Protestants, and most loyal Subjects of the Kingdom, have been prosecuted for a Sham-Conspiracy against the Government, the whole whereof was laid in Subornation, and supported by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury? Is it possible to be imagined, That unless they should be of as corrupt Principles, prostitute Consciences, and slavish Tempers, as those that have been contriving and carrying on the extirpation of our Religion, and the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of our Liberties, that they will ever sit calmly within those Walls, where their Ancestors have in all Ages so boldly asserted <hi>English</hi> Rights, and passed so many Laws for the security of them, without enquiring how the course of Justice hath been turned out of its ordinary and legal channel, and how the Law hath come to be applied to destroy a certain set of men, who for what appears, are singled out, and distinguished from others to be run down, because they cannot be so forward as some of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to betray their King, their Religion, and the Rights and Liberties of the Kingdom? Unless they who sit at the Helm, can obtain Members to be returned to serve in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in the manner that <hi>Jurors</hi> in some Counties have lately been, it is not to be conceived, but that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will in subserviency to a firm Union, and happy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondency with His Majesty; and in order to the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual preservation of his Life and Dignity, examine how the King hath been degraded from being the supreme Head, Governour, and Defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der of all his People, and influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to espouse a little Faction of men, and made as it were, to excl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de all the rest of his Subjects out of his Love and Care. Let no man think, that those who will be chosen to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100901:4"/>fill those honourable Seats, will ever have the baseness as to stile themselves the grand Inquest of the Nation, and His Majesties Supreme and High Council, without both looking into the late bold infraction of the Laws, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing those pernicious Advices, the effects whereof the whole Kingdom languisheth and groans under, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Authors of them. Nor will any Parliament this Generation is like to see, ever assume the immodesty, as to call themselves a part of the Legislative Power of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without inspecting the invasion that some have been endeavouring to make upon the Rights of Corporations and Cities, and how under a pretence of Legal <hi>Writs</hi> and <hi>Forms,</hi> the greatest Bodies <hi>corporate</hi> in the Kingdom, are brought into danger of losing the Priviledges and Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which they have for many Ages enjoy'd, not only by <hi>Charter,</hi> but by ancient <hi>Prescription,</hi> and by standing Laws. These are the things that must be expected from a true <hi>English</hi> Parliament, even tho His Majesty, in case of a Foreign War, and his being unable to preserve himself neutral, should joyn with the <hi>Confederates;</hi> which is that that his People do both universally desire, and will not fail to stand by him in, being once relieved from the dangers, their Lives, Religion and Fortunes have been brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Is it not therefore high time for the King to decline the prosecution of those Councils which will involve him in contests with his People, when he most needs their love and assistance? and to exchange those Ministers who have led him into courses which he cannot, as things are circumstanced, persevere in with safety, for others whose fidelity to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the wisdom of whose conduct may be relied upon? How easie were it for his Majesty to anticipate a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all the gracious things which the Kingdom either doth or can expect from one, by exerting his Power, and displaying his Wisdom and Goodness in effecting them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100901:5"/>and only leave to those great and honourable Bodies the opportunities of magnifying his Grace, and supplying his wants, with the punishing of some few of those that have abused his Name and Authority to countenance and justifie courses so unsafe and dishonourable to his Person, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to his people, and dangerous to his Crown and Dignity.</p>
            <p>And in case his Majesty upon the commencement and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress of a Foreign War, and his being necessitated to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouse one side or the other, should contrary both to the guidance and inclination of his own Understanding, and the true Interest of his people, be prevailed upon through the importunity of his Ministers to join with <hi>France,</hi> it is then demonstratively obvious, that the measures which have been taken, and in pursuance whereof designs are still carried on, will prove fatally pernicious in the issue and event. For as there are no hopes of obtaining any aids from a Parliament towards the management of a War in conjunction with a Nation which the <hi>English</hi> so generally hate, and to whose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence over some about his Majesty, they ascribe most of the Grievances whereof we complain; so should an Army be raised and maintain'd at the Kings own Charge for that Service, it is to be feared they would do as the <hi>Forces</hi> raised by the <hi>Decemviri</hi> against the <hi>Sabines</hi> did, of whom the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian tells us, that <hi>vinci se patiebantur, ne quid ductu aut auspicio Decemvirorum prospere gereretur,</hi> they suffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be beaten, rather than they would by conquering establish those new and harsh Masters in their Dominion. Nor ought our Ministers to forget how the Army that was raised in <hi>Anno</hi> 1640. to withstand the <hi>Scots,</hi> permitted themselves to be little better dealt with, as being possest with prejudices against the Ministers of that time, by reason of the intermission of Parliaments, and the invasion made upon Property by Ship-money, Billeting of Soldiers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100901:5"/>innumerable ways. Besides it is not easie to be imagin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d how the remembrance of a Sham-Plot to destroy the Lives of Protestants; how the entring <hi>Noli prosequi's</hi> to prevent the conviction of Miscreants for subornation and perjury; how the serving of a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> to take away the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the City; how the wheedling my Lord Mayor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all precedents as well as justice, to take Bond of a Gentleman to hold Sheriff of <hi>London,</hi> before he is Elected, or at least, confirmed, will ferment in the hearts of men, when upon our entring into a Confederacy with <hi>France,</hi> they find their Estates seised in all the <hi>Spanish</hi> Territories, their Ships taken by Pickaroons under the Authority of Commissions from the several Confederate Princes and States, and may be a Fleet of <hi>Dutch</hi> at the same time block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up our Harbours. And by how much the <hi>French</hi> King after he hath so long hector'd the world, begins now to flag in his Courage, declines in his Treasure, make submission to the Holy Father, whose Triple Crown he was so lately threatning to wrest from his Head, and comes to be so hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridly affronted by his Subjects and Relations, as he was lately in those base Attempts made upon the living Images of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; by so much will all the Protestants of <hi>England,</hi> scorn and disdain to be rendred at the pleasure of Two or Three Mushroom Statesmen, the supporters of his Throne. Nay, they do so warmly recent his ungrateful, as well as barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous carriage towards the <hi>French</hi> Protestants, that it were plainly to enrage the People of <hi>England</hi> to call them out to sustain that Monarch in his power of tyrannizing over those of the same Religion with themselves. Is not such a juncture as this, wherein the King is like to be obliged to enter into a War, by embracing one or the other of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending sides, a blessed and well-chosen season for reviving the Execution of the penal Laws against Dissenters, for ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> against the City of <hi>London,</hi> to wrest
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100901:6"/>their Charter from them, and for endeavouring against all Right and Custom, to fasten such a Sheriff upon them, who may return such Juries as will believe <hi>Barry, Macknamarra, Booth, Fitz-Gerald,</hi> &amp;c. and hang those out of the way that have the impudence to affirm there was a Popish Plot, or are such enemies to the Mother Church, as to wish, That His Majesty may out live the fears of a Popish Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor?</p>
            <p>And as no man pretending to Civil Wisdom, or who is so much as Master of common Sense, can think this a fit season for His Majesty, or any acting in his Name, and by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to go about to seise the City Charter, or unduly to obtrude a Sheriff upon them; so whosoever will narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enquire for the gratifying and obliging of what sort of persons all this is undertaken and attempted, he will find reason of acknowledging himself wonderfully surprised and amazed, that a loyal, great, and powerful City should be molested and disfranchised for the humouring men of their Figure, Principles and Complexion. For it is in the first place evident, that the Papists are the people whose Wishes and Designs are herein mostly befriended and complied with. For besides the malice they bear to <hi>London,</hi> both as it is the principal Seat, Harbour, and Sanctuary of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, and as it is the greatest Bulwark in <hi>Europe</hi> against <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish</hi> Tyranny, Superstition and Idolatry; so they can never forgive <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex</hi> the having furnished Juries for the Conviction of <hi>Coleman, Langhorn,</hi> and the rest of the late <hi>Romish</hi> Martyrs. Alas! those poor innocent Souls were guilty of nothing, but of conspiring the Death of an Heretical King, rooting out a Schismatical Nation, and designing the extirpation of a paltry Religion which hath for an Age or two infected these Northern Kingdoms; and yet this Fanatical City and County have found and suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jurors,</hi> who had no more wit nor honesty than to bring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100901:6"/>them in guilty of the Highest Treason. And tho the <hi>Papists</hi> do not hitherto judg it seasonable to mention it; yet it may be worth some peoples consideration of what stamp and character these <hi>Sheriffs</hi> were who returned those Juries, and to think with themselves how both they and all who serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either upon those <hi>Inquests</hi> or <hi>Trials,</hi> may in case we come once to have a Popish Prince, find this to rise in judgment against them. Can any man believe that they who burnt the City meerly for being a Nest of Hereticks, will after we have dipt in the Blood of their holy Fathers, and most Renowned Votaries, rest contented with turning this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Corporation</hi> into a Village? No, they will be satiated with no less than the Lives of Thousands, before we have sufficiently attoned for so heinous an offence. But as this is not the only, so it is not the main thing which the Papists propound unto themselves in obtaining the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to be men according to their humour and mind: For suppose they still entertain a design of destroying his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, and have either found another Doctor of <hi>Physick,</hi> or some little <hi>Cook,</hi> that have skill in the knack of Poyson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who are willing to do the meritorious Feat: Or sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that they are again provided of one or two bigotted Fellows who will be more careful of the Flints of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated Guns than <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Grove</hi> were, that have promised to do the sanctified job for them; Or suppose they are lately furnished with some Miscreants and Rascals, who being more bold and desperate than the Four Ruffians are prevailed upon by a pardon of all their sins, and an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of a large sum of money, with an assurance of preferment in some Popish State, to undertake and vow the executing this necessary piece of Service; would it not upon all or any of these supposals, be infinitely for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Papal Faction to have such <hi>Sheriffs</hi> over the City, upon whom, the Feat being done, they may consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100901:7"/>rely for the <hi>posse Londini,</hi> especially seeing they are not without apprehensions that there may be some even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the disgusted and persecuted Protestants, who may think both of enquiring after the manner of his death, and of endeavouring to revenge it. To the Papists we may sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join a little sort of people, who have been questioned by the Parliament, or discarded by their City-Masters; and these out of pure revenge would ravish the Charter from <hi>London,</hi> and do only press and employ the Kings Authority and Name to serve their particular malice, and to fight their personal quarrels. They will list themselves under any ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and enrol themselves in any party, provided they may but wreak their wrath, and retaliate the injuries which they fondly suppose they have received. And if their principles do not guide them to unite with the Papists, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance how they were treated by the same Authority that was zealous against the Catholicks, makes them cement with them, and co-operate in all their designs. And to these we may add a company of Nonsensical Fops, or Lunatick Fools, who being ambitious of an interest in the rising Faction, and covetous of being thought worthy of some Respect from the Factors for Popery and Arbitrary Power, do out of vanity, pride and ignorance, join in the noise, and cry for the seisure of the Charter, and the imposing a Sheriff up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City. These are a kind of brainsick fellows, who upon the hopes of being mounted upon the spoil and depression of the City Rights, offer themselves as Tools to serve and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish the designs of more subtil and malicious heads. In the last place, there are a company of Mercenary fellows, that used to serve as <hi>Tallymen</hi> in <hi>Guild-hall</hi> for their Groats a Cause; who being put by their Trade by the late Sheriffs, would, to recover their Four-pence a Trial, sell the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and all the Priviledges of this honourable Corporation. No observing man needs a Character whereby to know the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100901:7"/>sticklers against the Charter; the Loyalty upon which they so highly bear themselves, proclaiming them aloud in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and companies. For discourse them when you please, you will find them infinitely more fond of the Duke, than of the King; and carrying as if they had a dispensation to speak what they please of his Majesty, provided they do but adore and worship his Brother. Are not these fine Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that the Kings Name and Authority should be pressed and applied in their favour and service, tho to the disobli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a Loyal, Mighty, and Opulent City? Nor doth their Number bear any proportion to the noise and buz which they make; it being evident to every impartial Observer, that all their clutter is but like the disturbance which one or two broke out of <hi>Bedlam</hi> give the Town, which the grave Inhabitants think below their noticing, chusing to leave them to the hootings and discipline of the Boys. And would but our Governours make the experiment of giving one Weeks countenance to the other side, equal to what they have vouchsafed them for many Months, if not for some years, they would both see the boldest of them sneak and crouch, and their magnified Numbers shrivel and dwindle into nothing. Neither is this so ridiculous a proposal as some men may hastily imagine; for as it is not safe daily to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke and affront the Body of a City or a Kingdom, that know themselves more Loyal than those that are encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to teaze and abuse them; so it were a safe and easie way of knowing whether of the Two Parties into which our Ministers have so wisely divided the Nation, are not only the most firm and steddy with respect to their Temper and Principles, but the most considerable for their Quality, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Usefulness to the Government.</p>
            <p>Can any Protestant that values his Life, Liberty, or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, hold himself unconcern'd in the present Attempt of seising the Charter into the Kings hand, or of the project
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100901:8"/>of obtruding a Sheriff upon the Corporation whom them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves have not chosen, if he does but consider the end that is propounded in all this, and the Merciful and Just Design to which it is subservient? Such have been the Measures that have been taken, and the Counsels that have been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, that our Ministers, tho they know the Protestants wholly innocent from all ill intentions against his Majesty and the Government, yet do find it necessary for the justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Advices which they have given, and the courses that have been steered, to have us believed guilty of a Conspiracy against the King and the Monarchy. And therefore despairing of ever obtaining this, while there were men returned upon Juries that are either persons of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sense or moral honesty, they found no other way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying us under form of Law, but to get such thrust into the Office of Sheriffs of <hi>London,</hi> as will return persons who will be sure to convict and hang us, tho the things deposed against us be both impossible to be true, and inconsistent one with another. And there being a gang of fellows in the City that are ready to cut our throats for not being so furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for a Popish Successor, and so ambitious of becoming slaves as they are, were they not meerly restrained by the apprehensions that their own Lives would not be long safe, should they once attempt upon ours; how easie will it be, provided the Sheriffs be persons manageable by our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, to get a Grand <hi>Inquest</hi> impannell'd from among men of that inclination and temper, who will readily find any <hi>Bills</hi> against us that our mortal Enemies shall think conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to have us Indicted upon? Nay, how glad will these Cowards be, that only forbear knocking us on the head out of fear of our striking again, to have an opportunity put into their hands of destroying us without any further ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard than that of their souls, of which they are past being solicitous, having brought them into the utmost hazard ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100901:8"/>already, by their prodigious Oaths and unconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable Debaucheries. Let some men but once have the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of returning Juries in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex,</hi> and you shall soon see <hi>Barry</hi> and <hi>Fitzgerald</hi> step up and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence Credible Witnesses, notwithstanding the whole rational part of Mankind is fully satisfied and convinced of their being a Couple of suborned and perjured Rascals. Let not our Adversaries think, but that we do sufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the Design, in prosecution whereof, they are so zealous in wresting the Charter from the City, and so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious to impose a <hi>Sheriff</hi> upon us in the <hi>interim,</hi> to the defiance of all Right and Custom: For it is evident to all who do not wilfully shut their eyes, that it is in order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the Protestant Plot, and to have the Honours, Lives and Estates, both of the best and most eminent Citizens, and of the principal Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdom, at their disposal and discretion. For what else doth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto, to hear them say, That the King cannot have Justice in <hi>London,</hi> but that the Ministers who usurp his Name, cannot get their rage gratified by the Conviction and Condemnation of the D. <hi>M.</hi> E. <hi>S.</hi> E. <hi>E.</hi> S <hi>R. C. S P. W. S T. P.</hi> and multitudes besides, whom it were almost end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less to recount? Yet in the midst of all their clamor, we dare appeal to every man of Sense, Wit or Justice, whether there were ever better <hi>Juries</hi> than those that have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by these loyal and honest Gentlemen, who have ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Office of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> this and the last year? Did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver men of better Quality, greater Estates, clearer Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ation, or more excellent parts, appear either at the <hi>Old Baily, Guild Hall,</hi> or the <hi>Kings Bench Bar,</hi> than those whom the worthy Officers so boldly declaim'd against, have from time to time returned upon the Pannel? How often have <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Reverend Judges themselves, whom our adversaries have <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o reason to account partial in the favour of the Sheriffs,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100901:9"/>been forced to acknowledg the Wisdom, Justice and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of the late Juries, beyond whatsoever they observed in any they were upon the Tryal of Causes accustomed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to before? And this comfort the present and last <hi>Sheriffs</hi> are sure of, that no Reproach or Obloquy can fall upnon them, but it must affect the most knowing, the most vertuous, and the most loyal persons in the County and City, seeing it hath been their constant care to impannel such upon alloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, especially when any Cause was depending bet ween His Majesty and a Subject. And forasmuch as those whom they returned to serve upon the Indictment against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> were many of them persons whom their Countrey have often judged worthy to be chosen Members of the Honourable and Great Senate of the Nation, and wherein they acquitted themselves to the high satisfaction of that Learned, Wise, and August Body; they must be no less than Lunatick and Delirous, who upbraid and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> upon that score and account. And tho these worthy Gentlemen are become liable and exposed to the malice and reproach of a few Criminal persons, who know that themselves cannot be long safe, unless they can ruine the most loyal and best men in the Nation; yet it is to be hop'd that as they have now the praise and thanks of all true Protestants, good Subjects, and sincere <hi>English</hi> men; so they will be accounted in all ages to come the preserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their Prince from infamy and dishonour, and the Saviours and Defenders of their Country from destruction and ruine. But seeing a great cry hath been raised both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them and the <hi>London Juries,</hi> because of an <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> brought in upon an Indictment against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> where an Association, pretended to be found in his Study, was alledged in evidence and proof, it may not be amiss here to subjoyn a Form of an Association pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by the House of Lords, and that upon the motion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100901:9"/>and instigation of the Friends and Partisans of the Duke of <hi>York;</hi> the tenor whereof is as followeth:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="bill">
                        <head>A Bill depending in the House of Lords last Parliament at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and committed, with several Judges to assist, Judg <hi>Jones</hi> being one, for an Associa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to defend the Kings Life, and the Protestant Religion.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat all Bishops and Peers enter into this Association, or otherwise to be incapacitated to sit in Parliament: That no person be capable to be an Elector, or Elected into this, or any succeeding Parliament, until he hath entred into this Association: That all Judges, Mayors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of the Peace, and even Constable, and all Lord Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Deputy Lieutenants, Officers of the Militia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and all the Officers and Soldiers of His Majesties Guards and Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons, all Officers of the Admiralty and Ordinance, all Sea-Captains, and likewise all Ecclesiastical persons, as Deans,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rectors and Curates; all Bodies Corporate, as Colledges, Inns of Court,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>do enter into this Association; and that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son whatsoever, be permitted to have, or enjoy any Office or Place of Trust, Civil Military, or Ecclesiastical, who is not included in this Association.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100901:10"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That upon the Kings Death, be it violent or natural, all persons within the said Association, do immediately put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into Arms, and so to continue till the Parliament which is to meet at the Kings Death, be actually assembled; and there to obey such Orders as shall be given by Parliament. That the persons nominated by this Act to be the Heads of the Associati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be empowered to issue Commissions for the execution of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Law, and such Commissions to be of force from the time of the Kings Death, till the Parliament are met, and have enquired into the cause of the Kings Death; and no longer. That the</hi> Tower <hi>of</hi> London, Portsmouth, Plimouth <hi>and</hi> Hull, <hi>be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished Magazines: And that even in this Kings time, the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be commanded by such persons as shall be nominated by His Majesty, and approved in Parliament. That this Act of As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociation be not only read twice a year in every Church, but that the Association it self be posted up in every Church.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This is the Tenor of the Bill, that for the Preservation of the Kings Person, and the security of the Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion against the Designs of the Papists, the House of Lords were upon, and that not only with the concurrence, but at the motion and instigation of the Lords of His Majesties Privy Council, and the Duke of <hi>Yorks</hi> best friends. And tho possibly some that first advised this Bill might design no more by it than the obstruction of the <hi>Bill of Exclusion,</hi> which was then depending in the <hi>House of Commons;</hi> yet it would never have been so far countenanced in that Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable House, as to be committed, if they had not believed an <hi>Association</hi> consistent with the Government, as well as their Loyalty, and been apprehensive of the danger in which the Kings Person was, by reason of the Papists; whose Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will justify them in destroying an Heretical Prince at any time; but most especially when they hope thereby to make way for a Popish Successor to mount the Throne. And seeing no Evidence was produced that could influence the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100901:10"/>minds of wise and impartial men to believe that the <hi>Associ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> alledged against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> was ever seen by him, much less found in his Study; have we not reason to apprehend that it was only forged and invented to obtain an opportunity and advantage of breaking in upon, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculing the Wisdom and Authority of Parliaments? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I suppose our late Abhorrers of all <hi>Associations</hi> will see reason to bethink themselves what they have done, and to consider what a Judicature they have made themselves liable unto, by publickly exposing and detesting a thing, which not only His Majesties Hereditary Counsellors, but so great and honourable a part of the Legislative Authority of the Nation, judged expedient and necessary, as our affairs were then stated, and unhappily still continue, for the preservation of the Kings Person, and the defence of our Religion and Legal Rights.</p>
            <p>Nor is this matter wherein these persons are embark't, of obtruding a <hi>Sheriff</hi> upon <hi>London,</hi> and studying to ravish their Charter from them, of any less less consequence and import, than what involves the whole Nation in the resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, and reacheth all the Kingdom in the effects which it bodes and threatens. For what man is secure of his Right and Property, if Law and Ancient Prescription cannot preserve <hi>London</hi> in the quiet enjoyment of its Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions and Priviledges? There are few persons in the Kingdom, against whom by reason of the Transgression of some one Penal Statute or another, more may not be found to raise and commence a Suit in the Kings Name, than so far as we are able to judg by the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> is pretended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this noble and famous Corporation. And will not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man conceive himself unsafe in his Hereditary and Legal Rights and Property, when he finds that so great a City as <hi>London,</hi> is, without having done any thing Disloyal against His Majesty, only for some little, and as most believe, but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100901:11"/>supposed Transgression of their bounds, molested in the Possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ancient Franchises? Is it not rationally to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined that this attempt upon the Metropolis of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will be every where construed as a declaration of what all men are to expect, if there be but the least flaw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them to countenance the dis-seizing them of their Rights? Nor will it be here amiss to subjoin a Petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament to <hi>Edward</hi> the II. when they found that his Officers had such a Design on foot again <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex Rot. Claudo anno 19. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. Membr. 15.</note> as his Present Majesties Ministers seem now to have. <hi>A nostre Seigneour le Roi, auxieni prient les gents de la commune de votre Roialme, qu'il pleuse a votre haute Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur que voz citeins de votre Citee de Londres puissent rejoier lour Franchises custum — &amp; auncennes usages grantes de voz progenitours, &amp; de voz meismes confirmez demurer en lour force sumez estre attemptez per vos ministros pur ceo que nostre commune recoveriz est en la dite Citee.</hi> And tho that Prince was not very inclinable to hearken to good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, the neglect whereof ended in his ruine at last; yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on finding how the <hi>Prelates, Peers, Barons</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the attempts of his Ministers against <hi>London,</hi> as if done against themselves, he complied with their advices, as appears by the Answer which he returned; <hi>Il pend devant le Roi &amp; soit mande que drait soit fait per expresse bref redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Can any one believe that the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>England</hi> at this time are less sensible of the present Prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion commenced against the City, than their Progenitors anciently were? ought we not rather to conceive that were they once Assembled in Parliament, they would soon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press their resentments of what is doing, and make their applications to His Majesty with Humility, but yet earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness about it? By how much the Lords and Gentlemen of the Nation think their Personal safety endangered in the wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100901:11"/>the Right of choosing <hi>Sheriffs</hi> from the <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> by so much must they be concerned to lay this Design the more warmly to Heart. For what hath drawn so many persons of all ranks and qualities to take up their Residence in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Middlesex,</hi> but that continuing Loyal to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and the Government, they expect more impartiallity and Justice here, than they can look for in the Country? for which the Ministers having the proposing Sheriffs to His Majesty, are sure to take care that none shall be tendred, in order to be Prickt and Appointed, but such upon whom they can entirely depend, for returning Jurors according to their Humour and Mind.</p>
            <p>Nay, thinking people are the more astonished at these late Proceedings. when they consider, that never any of His Majesties Royal Predecessors, gave way to the like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs again the Metropolis of their Kingdom, save such as have been reckoned by all Historians in the number of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise and unfortunate Princes. For <hi>non quic quid nocens pati meretur, id egregio sub Principe statuendum est,</hi> A generous Monarch will not be severe towards offending Subjects, provided they do but retain their Loyalty, and persevere in their obedience. As it is most certain, that the City nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther claims nor practiseth any thing now, but what it hath been in the possession and usage of for divers Ages; so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any King, since <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Three hundred years ago, ever endeavoured to seise the City Charter into their hands. Whosoever consults the Story of our <hi>English</hi> Princes, will find, that those Kings have always been most prosperous both at home and abroad, who have been most gracious and favourable to the City of <hi>London.</hi> Nor did any thing prove more serviceable to that wise, and ever to be renowned Princess, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> than her treating <hi>London</hi> at all times, as her Darling and beloved City. How often hath the City been more faulty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100901:12"/>to divers of our former Kings, than the most impudent of its enemies dare say it hath been toward His Majesty? and yet none of them, since the time of the forementioned Prince, gave liberty to their Ministers to ravish from it its Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Rights. And it is not unworthy of some mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, that the reason why the <hi>Londoners</hi> did receive the Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> who was afterward <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th, so readily, and with so much joy and triumph into their City, and assist him so effectually against both his and their Leige Lord <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, was the remembrance of what that rash and unhappy Prince had done in the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning of their Magistrates, and annulling their Priviledges, and seising their Liberties, upon little and frivolous preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, into his own hands. Yea, so ungrateful a thing hath it always been to the People of <hi>England,</hi> to have <hi>Shcriffs</hi> imposed upon, and set over them, otherwise than according to the course and direction of the Law, that it was laid hold of, as one of the most plausible Reasons for deposing <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, when the Kingdom had rebelliously revolted from him, <hi>Quod Vicecomites nondum nominatos &amp; electos prout Lex statuerat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Knighton.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>sed pro suae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito voluntatis, &amp; pro suo &amp; aliorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo, ad gravamen populi sui, &amp; contra Leges Regni fecerat: That he had caused persons to be made Sheriffs according to his own humour, and for his own and others private advantage, to the great grievance of his People, and against the Laws of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for any of His Majesties Officers, or such as act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, to employ the Kings Authority and Name, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude a <hi>Sheriff</hi> upon the City, without the Election, or at the least, the confirmation of the Common-Hall; or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to wrest their Charter from them, when it doth not appear that they have forfeited it by any disloyal and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Crimes, is both the more dishonourable unto His
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100901:12"/>Majesty, and disgustful unto his Subjects, because the King hath not only so often, but so lately declared, That he will always govern according to Law. And what some little people are now upon against the City, added to divers things which in other Cases they have lately practised, makes men of reading and observation remember, how that after King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>First</hi> had published a Declaration upon his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving the Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1628. wherein he assured and promised all his Subjects to keep the Laws entire and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and to govern accordingly; yet immediately there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued an intermission of Parliaments for Twelve years, and an invasion upon Liberty and Property, by erecting of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolies, exacting of Loans, imposing and levying Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and illegal Imprisonments of His Majesties Liege peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Not that the blame of these things was to have been imputed to the late King, who is said to have been in his Temper, an excellent Prince, and who according to our Law, could do no wrong; but they were to have been as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to his Ministers, the Judges telling him, that they were legal and just, and his Council informing him, that they were for his Interest, and Actions every way safe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Nor will it, I fear, be enough to say, That in all which His Majesties Ministers are now in the pursuance of, the King proceeds in a legal way, and countenanceth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what there is a Right pretended for the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and justification of, seeing both the pretence of a Right where there is none, as in the Case of my Lord Mayors im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing a Sheriff upon the City, without the concurrence of the Livery-men; and also the observance of legal Forms, if the drift of the Law be not attended unto, does but ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der these things so much the worse in themselves, and the more odious and detestable by all Mankind. For whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is in <hi>fraudem Legis,</hi> is more disgustful than what is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly <hi>contra Legem.</hi> And people had rather be violently pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100901:13"/>and rob'd of their Possessions and Rights, than trickt and cheated out of them. For a Prince that would usurp Tyranny over a People (the thoughts whereof we believe His Majesty will always be averse from), need not put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the trouble and difficulty of abrogating, or declaring against Laws made to maintain the common Liberty; but he may both more safely and easily compass his Design, by getting those that have the administration of them under him, to interpret them as he pleases, and as doth best be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend him in his purposes. Nor were ever the Bulwarks of our <hi>English</hi> Laws, made ineffectual to the security of our Liberty and Estates, but when Privy-Councellors and Judges, who are sworn to advise their respective Princes to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws, as well as to conform thereunto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, did either neglect and despise, or arbitrarily and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly expound them. For not to mention what the Judges and Ministers in the late Kings time said was just and legal, tho when it came to be examined in Parliament, it was found subversive of all our Laws and <hi>English</hi> Rights; Did not <hi>Trisilian</hi> and <hi>Belknap,</hi> by imposing arbitrary and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Expositions upon our Laws to <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress the whole Kingdom, and prove an unhappy means and occasion of alienating the love of his People from him, and therein of laying the foundation of all the misfortunes and miseries that fell upon him? Nor did the Right which they claimed as Judges of interpreting and declaring the sense and meaning of Laws, save them from the punishments which the breaking their own Oaths, and making the King violate the Oath which he had taken at his Coronation, for the well and good ruling of his people, had made them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve and become liable unto. For the Lord Chief Justice <hi>Tresilian</hi> was by judgment of the House of Lords hang'd at Tyburn, having first been drawn through <hi>London</hi> streets, and <hi>Belknap</hi> being upon the intercession of the Queen and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100901:13"/>others pardoned, as to the Sentence of Death, he was out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law'd, and for ever banisht into <hi>Ireland.</hi> Yea, did not the Judges who took upon them arbitrarily to expound and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Law in King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>first</hi>'s time, fall all of them under the censure of Parliament; and had not one of their Heels done his Head a courtesie, he was sure to have died for it? How ill will some men deserve of the King, if the things which they hrve put him upon cannot, after all their endeavours, be carried? And what are they to expect from a Parliament, if the advice which they have given, be found unjust and pernicious? Nor will it be a small aggravation of their Crime, that they have put His Majesty upon these things, after he had so often declared upon the Word of a Prince, That he would always govern according to Law. It would really grieve any one that loves the Person of his Prince, or that desires the honour and security of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to hear what kind of Discourse is the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that a man shall meet with in all Companies. For says <hi>one,</hi> Is this His Majesties ruling according to Law, to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Authority to be employed to divert the edg of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice from one sort of his Subjects, and to permit the Law to be turned against others in the extreamest rigour? Is this, says <hi>another,</hi> His Majesties making the Law the standard and measure of his Government, to preserve those whom Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments have impeached as guilty of the highest Crimes, and at the same time, through the influence of the guilty and accused, to apply it to the distress and ruine of those that the great Senate of the Kingdom do judg both the Kings honour, and the preservation of our Religion and Liberties to depend upon? What an unhappy posture are we in, says a <hi>third,</hi> that a mighty and opulent Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and which is our Monarchs Royal Chamber, shall be attack'd in their Rights and Priviledges; and that the pleasing and obliging a Popish presumtive Heir, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100901:14"/>may be only for the gratifying of an upstart Knight, who had all his days remained upon the level with the meanest Gown-man, had not the Cities honouring him in and by their Service, given him an opportunity of frequent access to his Majesty, to whose Benignity and Grace, in the lack of all personal merit, he is indebted for his exaltation and rise. The Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex,</hi> says a <hi>fourth,</hi> were never reproached for the return of the Jury that acquitted Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> tho his flight since is no small evidence of his guilt; and must they be not only every day exposed for the return of the <hi>Pannel</hi> that brought in an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon the Bill against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> whose innocency as to the Crimes whereof he was accused, does every day appear more evident and illustrious; but must this be turned and improved into an occasion of offence against the whole Corporation, and made a justifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ground of stripping and divesting the City of its Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and Priviledges? <hi>Hobb</hi>'s state of Nature is much more desirable, says a <hi>fifth,</hi> than to live under a Government where when men upon the performance and discharge of their duty towards their Rulers and one another, expect to have equal favour and protection from those that are over them, do instead thereof become the objects of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates jealousie, and are surrender'd to be prey'd upon by their fellow-subjects. Are the pretended Crimes, says a <hi>sixt,</hi> upon which the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> is served against the City, of yesterday's standing, and of late date? Or where have they lien dormant all this while? Are Mr. <hi>Duboise</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillion,</hi> saith <hi>another,</hi> such stupid and nonsensical Fops in comparison of Politick Sir <hi>John Peak,</hi> and Sir <hi>Simon Lewis,</hi> as that a project should be set on foot of debarring and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding these as persons incapable of serving his Majesty and the City, while these were welcom'd into their Office as men not only admirably qualified for the place, but as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100901:14"/>Instruments through their vast and acquired prudence, both to sustain the weight of that Employment, and to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and raise the Honour of his Majesties Government. Nay, says another, this proceeding from favourers of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry about his Majesty, is but a <hi>preludium</hi> of what we are to expect when Papal Counsels shall only obtain. For we have a pattern, says he, of what it is to govern according to Law, in a Proclamation by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Burnets <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Records to the</hi> 2d <hi>part of the Hist. of Reform.</hi> p. 114.</note> the tenor whereof is, That those to whom it was directed, should do such and such things as are there mentioned and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>any Laws or Statutes to the contrary notwithstanding.</hi> And as these are some of the Reflections that are commonly made upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent proceedings; so it is impossible while men have not the command of their understandings, to judg otherwise than the state and nature of things guide them unto, but that their loaded and overburden'd minds should vent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in such expressions as these are.</p>
            <p>But doth my Lord Mayor consider what he is about, and wherein such an attempt may issue, as his imposing a Sheriff upon the City without the Confirmation of a <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> seeing he cannot but understand that both the Laws and uninterrupted Custom of the <hi>Corporation,</hi> do positive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly require and direct the contrary? Will it not be enough to embalm his Memory, That his being in the Chair hath been that which hath principally encouraged some little men to obtain the serving of a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> upon the City for the seizing of their Charter, but must he to the further glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and reputation of his Name, both forget his Trust, and by such an Act as This, give up the Liberties and Lives of his fellow Citizens to the Will, Malice, and Rage of some mean, ill-principled, and implacable men? For his Lordship cannot be so void of Understanding, as not plainly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100901:15"/>That it is only in order to Hang such Protestants a Sir <hi>G. J.</hi> and those Ministers whose Tool he is, are incensed against, that he hath been so often and so importunately pressed to this method and course that he is entred upon, and still seems inclinable to persevere in. Nor can he think but that Mr. <hi>Duboise</hi> and Mr. <hi>Papillon</hi> are as prudent and honest Gentlemen, and as capable to serve his Majesty and the City, as that person is to whom his Lordship hath been pleased to drink; and that should they be chosen Sheriffs, they will discharge their Office with as much Loyalty as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Mr. <hi>North</hi> himself can be supposed to do. And if his Lordship's present Greatness and honourable Station have not made him lose his sense, methinks he should easily smell and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prehend some bad Design, in finding himself at such a juncture, put upon the obstructing the choice of two such worthy and deserving persons. It would now seem that it was not for nothing that some people were so zealous, and did so industriously stickle for Sir <hi>John Moor</hi>'s Election to the <hi>Chair;</hi> for it appears they knew in the service of what design they should use his Lordship, and what point they hop'd to gain by his carrying the Sword. Nor was it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cause that the news of his being chosen Mayor was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with no small joy and triumph at <hi>Holy Rood House,</hi> for some behind the curtain had undoubtedly laid the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of serving themselves in this, if not other considerable matters, by him. But forasmuch as my Lord hath been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore reported to be an honest and well meaning Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, tho he was never conceived to be so great a Politician as to be able to penetrate into the hidden designs of States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or see through the plausible pretences of crafty and subtil people; it may not be amiss for him to consider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this which he hath suffered himself to be prevailed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto, be agreeable to the Charters and Customs of the City, and consistent with the Oath which he hath taken to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100901:15"/>observe and keep them. And as we doubt not to prove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, That the Right of Electing Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> doth both by Charter and constant Usage belong to the <hi>Barons</hi> or Free-men, as well as to my Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen; so it may not misbecome his Lordship to think what honour from others, or peace in himself he is like to have, if he violate his Oath, and trample upon the Rights and Priviledges of the Corporation. But if through a fear of displeasing some great men, he should be influenced to forget the Obligations he is under by virtue of his Trust and Oath, yet let the kindness which he retains for his Liberty, Life, and Estate, prevail with him to consider wherein he is embarking, and what his pretended Advisers and daily Visitants do put him upon. For as the being Lord Mayor does not give him an Arbitrary power, so he is liable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to an account for every violation of the City-Rights, and for all Offences against the Faith and Trust which are reposed in him. And how much any Crime he becomes guilty of in the exercise of his Government, proves pernicious and fatal in the consequences of it, by so much ought he to reckon himself liable sooner or later to the greater punishment. And let me as a friend to his Lordship tell him, That in the 50 of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. not only several were disfranchised for Offences contrary to their Oaths as Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, but that one <hi>Ellis</hi> and some others were impeached in Parliament for Crimes of that kind. And his own memory will serve to instruct him, how that <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. Sir <hi>Richard Gurney</hi> was impeached by the House of Commons for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to his Oath, and the Faith and Trust reposed in him as Mayor, endeavoured to bring in an Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment into the City, and to overthrow the ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms and Usages thereof, and for which he was censured by the House of Lords to be incapable to bear any Office of Honour or Trust in the Commonwealth, to be degraded of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100901:16"/>all Honours and Titles, and to continue Prisoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> during the Pleasure of Parliament. And whatever Exceptions that Impeachment is liable unto, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the matters whereof he was accused; yet it serveth to declare the power of Parliaments over Lord <hi>Mayors</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and how they are obnoxious to answer for Crimes against the Customs and Usages of the Corporation. And it were ridiculous to imagine, how their Lordships, in case they transgress, should have a Priviledg to escape animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, when the greatest Peers in the Realm, the most immediate Ministers of our Kings, and the highest Officers of the Kingdom, are subject to the Authority and Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Parliaments, and often made to feel the effects of their Justice.</p>
            <p>And as this Usurpation upon the Rights of the City, was little expected from Sir <hi>John Moor;</hi> so his carriage in this Affair, shows us how far some people may be deceived in the opinion which they entertain of men, and what little trust there is to be given for the future, to the representations which some make of their own Principles and Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 'Tis true, there were a great many Citizens, and even of those who had no ill thoughts of him in the general, that yet knowing the easiness of his Nature, believed he would not be able to pursue and follow his own inclinations, but that he would be carried away by the torrent of great mens importunities, if not hector'd by their Rant, and huff into whatsoever they had a mind unto; and therefore were willing to have adjourned his exaltation to the Mayoralty, till a season that might have better accorded with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Temper, and when heats and passions might be more allay'd among our selves, and dangers fewer, and less threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from our enemies. Nor was this out of any quarrel against his Lordships person, but meerly with respect to our own safety, and for the preserving our selves from ruine,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100901:16"/>and to prevent the inconveniencies which we foresaw the facility of his Nature would run both himself and us into. And this courtesie we had infallibly done him, and been withal so kind to our selves as became us, had not the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, according to their wonted prospect, and usual pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, concurred many of them in his Election, and thereby derived all those difficulties upon him, themselves, and us, which have since ensued, and wherewithal we are now wrest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and contending. However, I hope the fruits which they have seen of their precipitancy, and want of distrust, will instruct them to be more cautious and discreet for the future, than to chuse one to the Chair in such a critical jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, upon no better motive than meerly because he is next to it.</p>
            <p>But now in case his Lordship should not only neglect his Honour, sacrifice his Conscience, but venture his Life, as well as his Estate, if that he may but gratifie half a dozen of people, and give them an opportunity of hanging what Protestants they have a mind to; yet it is the concernment of the Gentleman whom he pretends to honour, by calling him to the Office of Sheriff, not to suffer himself to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy'd and coax'd into a noose by his Lordship. For whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever enters upon the Sherifalty of <hi>London,</hi> that is not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, and according to Charter elected thereunto, will both find himself liable to be proceeded against, as an usurper of that Office, and be made accountable for whatsoever he does in the pretended discharge of it. There is not a Writ he executes, nor a person he detains in hold, nor any that he shall see the Sentence of the Law executed upon, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so legally, and for never so heinous Crimes Convicted and Condemned, but he is to expect to have it all rise in Judgment against him, and to be made answerable for it. For as it is the Law alone that gives him his Authority and Power, and protects him for all that he does in the legal
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100901:17"/>exercise of it; so it conveys no Right, Jurisdiction or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority unto him, but upon the supposal, that he is elected and chosen in the manner which the City-Charter prescribes, and according to the custom and usage of the Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And it is as lawful and safe for a <hi>Porter</hi> at the Exchange, to take upon him to keep men in prison and duress, or to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the execution and serving of Writs, or to claim the seeing Malefactors hang'd, as it is for one that pretendeth to the Office of Sheriff of <hi>London,</hi> upon no better foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation than my Lord Mayors drinking to him at the <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house.</hi> Nay, there is not a Serjeant, Bayliff, or the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Officer under him, but is liable to be punished for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever they do, either in the pursuance of an Authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him, or upon the immediate execution of his Commands, and obeying of his Orders. And therefore should my Lord Mayor insist upon his having drunk to a Gentleman, as a good and formal Election of him to the <hi>Sheriffwick,</hi> yet if that Gentleman be not delirous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated, he will never hazard his Liberty, Fortune and Life, in the undertaking an Office that he is not better and more loyally called unto.</p>
            <p>So vain, foolish and groundless is this pretended Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Right of my Lord Mayors electing a person to be <hi>Sheriff</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> by the Ceremony of drinking to him, that there is not so much as one man in the whole City, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of those that now seem to allow of it, but that he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther already hath, or will at one time or another find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self obliged to contemn and withstand so great and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Usurpation upon his Rights and Liberties. And tho some mad and phantastical fools may in the pursuance of the animosities which are raised both in City and Kingdom, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiesce in such a Choice, when they find it to the gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their malice and revenge against those whom pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and Popish bigottedness make them differ from; yet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100901:17"/>they will be as ready as any to withstand and abhor it, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the Tables shall so far turn, as that we have a Mayor who will think it convenient, and even needful, to drink to one of the contrary and opposite Party. Yea, did not the very persons that are now so zealous for the justification of this matter, and supposed legality of electing one of the Sheriffs by my Lord <hi>Mayors</hi> drinking to him, but a year a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go both ridicule this won<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Ceremony, and endeavour to put by <hi>Alderman Pilkinton,</hi> whom Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> the then Lord Mayor, had drunk unto? And did they not in contempt and defiance of this claimed Right of the <hi>Mayor,</hi> and usual and much celebrated Rite of drinking, endeavour to seclude the person to whom, according to this new ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated Mode, the <hi>Sheriffwick</hi> had been adjudged; and both put up and Voted for Sir <hi>Humphrey Nicolson,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Box,</hi> the persons they would have had <hi>Sheriffs</hi> for the year that was to ensue?</p>
            <p>Having, as well as we are able, discoursed the foregoing Heads, we are to advance in the next place, to set it beyond all contradiction and control, That the Right of chusing the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> does by Charter, as well as common usage, lodg not in the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> alone, but in him, the Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> And as it is not easie to declare the Antiquity of this great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable City, so no more are we capable to assign the time when it first had such Magistrates and Officers, as those we do stile <hi>Sheriffs.</hi> But this we learn from <hi>Stephanides,</hi> who wrote in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> I. That even then <hi>Civitas</hi> London <hi>habuit annuos pro consulibus Magistratus vicecomites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex M. ss. in Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. Cotton.</note>
               <hi>the City of</hi> London <hi>had besides all other Magistrates, yearly Sheriffs.</hi> Nay, we learn from a <hi>Plea</hi> put in by the City, in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th, upon a Cause depending before Commissioners appointed by the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100901:18"/>King, between the said <hi>City,</hi> and St. <hi>Martins le Grand,</hi> That <hi>Gulielmus Conquestor authoritate Parliamenti, &amp; per duas Cartas quas Major &amp; Cives proferunt &amp; verificare para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti sunt, dimisit Civibus</hi> London <hi>totam dictam Civitatem &amp; Vicecomitatum:</hi> William <hi>the Conquer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> demised and granted to the Citizens of</hi> London,
<note place="margin">Lib. K. fol. 120.</note>
               <hi>by the authority of Parliament, and by two Charters, the whole City and Sheriffwick of</hi> London. And for the <hi>Sheriffwick of Middlesex,</hi> they have always enjoy'd it at the yearly <hi>Rent</hi> of 300. <hi>l.</hi> since <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>first</hi>'s time. For that King granted <hi>Civibus</hi> Lond. <hi>&amp; Heredibus suis, Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitatum</hi> Lond. <hi>&amp; de</hi> Mid. <hi>To the Citizens of</hi> London, <hi>and their Heirs, the Sheriffwicks of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesex. And <hi>King John</hi> in the first year of his Reign, granted and confirmed to the Citizens and their Heirs, <hi>Vicecomitatum</hi> London <hi>&amp; de</hi> Middlesex, <hi>&amp;c. the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Middlesex, <hi>with all the customs to the</hi> Sheriffwicks <hi>belonging, to be enjoyed by them and their Heirs freely and quietly, honourably and wholly, by the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farm of</hi> 300. <hi>l. per Annum.</hi> And in the 11th, year of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> they had by another Charter the said <hi>Sheriffwicks</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex</hi> demised and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed unto them, with all the Things and Customs thereunto belonging. Now all these <hi>Charters</hi> have by <hi>inspeximus</hi>'s been confirmed under the great Seal of <hi>England, by Edward</hi> 1. <hi>Edward</hi> 2. <hi>Edward</hi> 3. <hi>Richard</hi> 2. <hi>Henry</hi> 4. <hi>Henry</hi> 5. <hi>Henry</hi> 6. <hi>Edward</hi> 4. <hi>Richard</hi> 3. <hi>Henry</hi> 7. <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the 1st, <hi>and his present Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor were these <hi>Charters,</hi> so far as any of them relate to the <hi>Sheriffwick</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Original <hi>Grants,</hi> but only <hi>Confirmations</hi> of what the City had by <hi>prescription</hi> pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd and enjoy'd long before. For the late Lord Chief
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100901:18"/>Justice <hi>Hale</hi> said well and truly in a Case wherein being a <hi>Barrester,</hi> he and Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> were Councel at an Argument in <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Lond. <hi>Liberties, or an Argument of Law and Reason,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Printed by</hi> J. Cotteril <hi>for</hi> Giles Calvert. 1651.</note>
               <hi>Decemb.</hi> 14. 1650. concerning the Right of Electing the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> namely, that the <hi>Charters</hi> were only <hi>confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and not <hi>Originals,</hi> forasmuch as the City had time out of mind enjoy'd the Officers of <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs</hi> by <hi>Prescription.</hi> And for the <hi>Sheriffwick</hi> of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> they have held and enjoy'd it by <hi>Charter</hi> ever since the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> the 1st, at the yearly rent above mentioned. And whereas the <hi>Charters</hi> of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d. say, <hi>concessimus &amp; confirmavimus civibus Londini vicecomitatum de Midd. We have devised and grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Citizens of</hi> London <hi>the Sheriffwick of Middlesex;</hi> it is plain that these were not Original <hi>Grants,</hi> but only <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> seeing <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>first</hi> had granted the <hi>Sheriffwick</hi> of <hi>Middlesex</hi> to the <hi>Citizens</hi> of <hi>London</hi> before. And by the way, forasmuch as in the information upon the <hi>Writ</hi> of <hi>Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto</hi> brought against the City, <hi>they are to shew by what War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant they Nominate, Elect and constitute Sheriffs of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Middlesex, <hi>to execute and make return of all Writs, Bills and Precepts Domini Regis infra civit' Londini &amp; commita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Midds. pro administratione &amp; executione Justitiae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>absque commissione, sive literis patentibus a Dom. Rege obtentis, of our Lord the King in the said City and County, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration and execution of Justice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without commission or Letters Patents from the King.</hi> We therefore say that all the <hi>Charters</hi> bearing not only a <hi>Grant</hi> and <hi>confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the said <hi>Sheriffwicks,</hi> but of all the <hi>Things, customs</hi> and <hi>priviledges</hi> which thereunto belong, there is no need of any particular clause in the said <hi>Charters,</hi> as to those Articles, seeing it is plainly implyed in the Demised and Confirmed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100901:19"/>
               <hi>things and customs▪</hi> yea, the very Grant of the <hi>Sheriffwick</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves a concession of those Powers and Authorities. And for any to imagine the contrary, is to make the <hi>Charters</hi> of all the Corporations in <hi>England</hi> insignificant, and to instigate the King to disseise His Leige People of their Rights upon a meer <hi>Quillet</hi> and Trick. And tho such little arts may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Sr. <hi>G. J.</hi> and Mr. <hi>S.</hi> yet they are below the honour, and inconsistent with the wisdom and justice of a Prudent and Great Prince. Nor is it unworthy of our Remark, that the Act of Parliament of the <hi>first</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d, which confirms unto the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> all the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Customs which they had enjoy'd in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>confessor</hi> and other Progenitors of the said <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d. expresly says that the City had divers Liberties and Priviledges not only by the <hi>Charters,</hi> but, <hi>fine Cartis ex antiquâ consuetudine, without</hi> Charters, <hi>namely by Prescription and ancient customs.</hi> And how easie were it to assign divers Priviledges and Rights of the City, of which there is not the least mention in any <hi>Charter,</hi> which yet upon Bills, Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Tryals, have been acknowledged rightfully to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain and belong unto them by vertue of Prescription and Ancient Usage. For as Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> said in his Argument at <hi>Guild-Hall, Dec.</hi> 14. 1650. <hi>The</hi> Charters <hi>of the City do not give them a Right, but are only matter of confirmation of the Rights which they immemorially had; and that their Officers were before</hi> Charters, <hi>and not instituted by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all the Rights that are dimised and comfirmed by <hi>Charter</hi> to the City of <hi>London,</hi> are not only granted to the <hi>Mayor,</hi> but to the <hi>Free-men</hi> and <hi>Baroms.</hi> For the Tenor of them all is either <hi>Civibus nostris London,</hi> as in the <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Rich.</hi> the <hi>first,</hi> and the <hi>Charter</hi> granted by King <hi>John,</hi> and that of the 11 of <hi>Hen</hi> 3. And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Right of chusing Sheriffs is dimised, granted and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100901:19"/>confirmed to the Citizens and Free-men. For the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the first year of King <hi>John</hi> expresly says, <hi>Concessimus Civibus</hi> London, <hi>quod ipsi de seipsis faciant vicecomites quos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque voluerint, &amp; amoveant quando voluerint, We have granted to the Citizens of</hi> London, <hi>that they shall elect from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves what Sheriffs they please, and remove them when they please.</hi> Accordingly <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> in a <hi>Writ</hi> directed to the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs</hi> in the 8th. year of his Reign, takes notice, that by the <hi>Charters of his progenitors the Kings of England, it had been granted, Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus praedictae civitatis, quod ipsi vicecomites de seipsis quos vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerint eligant, to the Citizens of</hi> London, <hi>that they should from amongst themselves chuse and elect such Sheriffs as they pleased and thought good.</hi> This is the Tenor in which all the <hi>Charters</hi> run, and the custome and usage of electing hath been always conformable hereunto, as we shall make appear anon.</p>
            <p>Nor does the Right of the City, as to the power of chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Sheriffs, or in reference to the priviledges which they have anciently enjoyed, depend meerly either upon <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription</hi> or <hi>Charter,</hi> but they are confirmed and secured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes.</hi> The Great <hi>Charter</hi> of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>England</hi> which was first Granted in the 17th. year of King <hi>John,</hi> and renewed in the 9th. year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med above <hi>thirty</hi> times in Parliament since, does particularly provide, <hi>that the City of</hi> London <hi>shall have all her Liberties and Customs which she was used to have.</hi> And as that <hi>Charter</hi> is but Declarative of the Rights which belonged to the People of <hi>England</hi> by the Common Law of the Land; so it supposeth <hi>London</hi> to have had many Liberties and Priviledges peculiar to it self, all which it confirms unto them by the same unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Law that it secured the Rights of the Kingdom. Yea, the Liberties, Priviledges and Jurisdictions of <hi>London</hi> are in a most especial manner ratified and confirmed by Act in the <hi>first</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> 3d, in which that great King grants and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100901:20"/>unto them, not only, <hi>omnes libertates &amp; antiquas suas consuetudines, all their liberties and ancient customes which they either had at the time of making the Great</hi> Charter, <hi>or which had been granted by the</hi> Charters <hi>of any of his progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (of which the Right of chusing their own Sheriffs, was one); but, diversas Libertates &amp; consuetudines, quas sine Cartis ex antiqua consuetudine habuissent, divers Liberties and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms which they had and enjoyed without</hi> Charters, <hi>namely, by perscription.</hi> And there is <hi>One</hi> Remarkable Clause in that Act, viz. <hi>Et quod pro aliqua personali trangressione, vel judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio personali alicujus ministri ejusdem civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actus Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect. 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>non capiatur Libertas civitatis illius in manus nostras, vel Haeredum nostr'; That the Liberties of that said City shall not be taken into the hands of us or our Heirs, for any perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Trangression or Judgement of any Minister of the said City.</hi> Nor is this Act single and Solitary in this matter, but there is another in a Parliament the 7th. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. wherein that King upon the Petition of the Commons, comfirms unto them all their <hi>Franchises</hi> and Priviledges,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Parliam.</hi> 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect.</hi> 8. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi.</hi>
               </note> and that with this Clause, <hi>Sive usi non fuerint, fivi abusi fuerint, whether they were either such as they had abused, or had not made use of.</hi> And it is most probable that King <hi>Richards</hi> violating this Law by the seisure of the City <hi>Charter</hi> in the 16th, year of his Reign, was part of the reason of the 16th Article against him, upon which among others they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed him; namely, <hi>That he the said King not willing to keep the just Laws and customs of his Kingdom, but according to his Arbitrary will, to do, quicquid desderiis eius occurreret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">viz. <hi>Kingston.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>whatsoever should occur to his desires,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>had said, quod ipse solus possit mutare &amp; condere leges Regni sui, That he himself alone
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100901:20"/>could make and change the Laws of his Kingdom.</hi> And the Attempt of <hi>Richard</hi> 2. in the seising of the City-Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his hands, having not only greatly alarm'd all the other Cities and Burroughs, but wonderfully disgusted the whole Kingdom, may be the Reason why in the Reign of succeding Kings,
<note place="margin">See Rast. Stat. 2 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 4 <hi>H</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 9 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.13 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note>
               <hi>we have the Liberties and Franchises of all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Burroughs of the Realm, confirm, and secured by Acts of Parliament, and that equally with the Liberties and Franchises of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and all other Leige People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And according to the tenor of the <hi>Charters</hi> which have been so confirmed by Acts of Parliament, have the Free-men, together with my Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, from time to time elected and chosen <hi>Sheriffs.</hi> It is true, there have been some variations, as to the numbers and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of Free-men that have been admitted to chuse; but there was never to this day a <hi>Sheriff</hi> constituted over the City, by the meer Authority of the <hi>Mayor,</hi> or the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority</hi> of the Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> without the concurrence, choice and confirmation of the greater part of those Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who have made up the Common-Hall. Anciently all the Free-men had a Vote in the Election of the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs;</hi> but that growing impossible to be practised, through the vastness of the number of Free-men, and that manner and form of chusing those Officers having been often at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Riots, the City thought fit to regulate it; but still with this Reservation and Provision, That no <hi>Mayor</hi> nor <hi>Sheriff</hi> should be chosen without the Concurrence, Vote and constitutive Consent of a competent number of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Thus we find, That in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> 1. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> 2. and some part of <hi>Edward</hi> 3. the Sheriffs were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen by the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen,</hi> and a <hi>cettain number of good
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100901:21"/>and loyal men,</hi> out of the several and respective <hi>Wards.</hi> For we find, that in the sixth of <hi>Edward</hi> 1. <hi>Vicecomites electi fuerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. A. fol. 121.</note>
               <hi>per Majorem, Aldermanos, &amp; probos homines Civitatis, the Sheriffs were chosen by the Mayor, Aldermen, and the good or lawful men of the City.</hi> And in the 31, 33, 34, <hi>Edward</hi> 1. and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. we find, that they were chosen by <hi>the Mayor, Aldermen, and Twelve Free-men out of every Ward.</hi> But in all that time, we have not one word of the <hi>Mayor</hi>'s having a Right, by his Prerogative, to chuse one of the Sheriffs; but from the 20th of <hi>Edward</hi> 3. which is above 200 years since the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> of <hi>London</hi> have been always chosen by the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen, Common-Council, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very-men.</hi> And as the Rights granted to the City by the Charter, of chusing their <hi>Sheriffs</hi> from among themselves, is hereby truly preserved, the Free-men still chusing, tho every Free-man doth not chuse; so this is both a prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and usage of too long a date, and a form and manner of electing, the benefits and advantages whereof we have so fully tasted, that the present Mayor ought not either out of a <hi>Capricio</hi> of his own, or at the instigation of others, who design no less than the destruction of many principal Citizens, to attempt the wresting so useful, necessary, and well established a Right from the City.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, that ever since about the 20th of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> my Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> hath had the naming or proposing one person for the <hi>Shrivalty</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex;</hi> but his nomination was never held to constitute the said person <hi>Sheriff,</hi> or to preclude the free choice of the Commons. Nor may it be amiss briefly here to unfold both the first oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of, and the moving Reason unto it. The occasion seems to have been this, That whereas a Parliament held in the 20th <hi>Edward</hi> 3. had made a Law, That Justices of <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>size</hi> should enquire into the Misdemeanours of <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100901:21"/>punish them as well at the Kings Suit, as the parties, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as Law and Reason should require; thereupon many Citizens that were qualified to serve the City in the Office of Sheriffs, being fearful and timorous, lest upon little mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages in that Trust, they might bring their Liberties and Estates into danger, used to withdraw themselves, in order to decline their being Elected. Therefore there was the same year an Ordinance made by the Lord Mayor, certain Aldermen, and the Sheriffs, <hi>de assensu totius commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, with the assent and concurrence of the Commonalty, That if any absented himself out of the City at the day of the Election of Sheriffs, he should pay to him that should be chosen, by his withdrawing and default, the sum of</hi> 100 l. and that the <hi>Mayor,</hi> who is supposed to have better knowledg than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which of the Citizens are most fit for so weighty an Office, <hi>should present and nominate one person to the Commons, in order to the being chosen Sheriff.</hi> And yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Ordinance, we do not find that ever the Mayor as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed the Authority of imposing whom he had named, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City; but the Commons have always enjoyed the Right of refusing or confirming the Person Nominated and Presented. And as the <hi>Mayors</hi> nominating a Person, was never transacted at the <hi>Bridg</hi>-House, till since the Reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. so he always took the advice of his Brethren the <hi>Aldermen,</hi> whom he should recommend as a person in his or their Opinion worthy to be Elected Sheriff. Hence during all the time from the 20 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. till the 1st <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. we not only read that <hi>apud Ghihaldam,</hi> such and such a one was named by the <hi>Mayor;</hi> but that they were always Presented to the <hi>Commons, nomine Majoris &amp; Aldermanorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' later Ages have brought what used to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facted in the Court of <hi>Hustings</hi> at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> to be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at a Dinner at the <hi>Bridg-House,</hi> and hath connived at a greater Arbitrariness of naming and presenting in the <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or,</hi> than anciently belonged unto, or was claimed by him;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100901:22"/>yet no one Mayor till Sir <hi>John Moor,</hi> ever placed so much in Drinking to a person, so as upon that to require Bond of the person Drunk unto to hold <hi>Sheriff,</hi> before he is so much as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented unto, much less confirmed by the <hi>Common-Hall.</hi> And tho' those whom former Mayors have usually named, have been seldom refused or rejected by the <hi>Commons;</hi> yet this did not arise from any Right in the <hi>Mayor,</hi> by vertue of the Prerogative of his Place, to Elect one, or that the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> were obliged tamely to acquiesce in whomsoever he Presented; but because our Mayors have been for the most part so modest and discreet, as to nominate such persons which were acceptable to the City, and Gentlemen of that Worth, Justice and Integrity, that the Citizens themselves knew not where to find better. And indeed the Priviledg vouchsafed my Lord Mayor, of naming and tendring one to the <hi>Hall</hi> for <hi>Sheriff,</hi> was to serve the interest, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the safety of the whole City, and not to gratifie the humour and rancour of a little venomous and factious Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it was in subserviency to the equal preserving the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Lives of all the Free-men, and not to sacrifice the most useful in the Corporation, to the revenge of their Enemies: Yet even heretofore the <hi>Commons</hi> have found cause to assert their Priviledges and Rights, and not implicitely to acquiesce in every one whom their <hi>Mayors</hi> had nam'd unto them. For besides, that whensoever any person whom my L. Mayor hath named by the Solemnity of drinking, and prickt with a kind of Authority for the ensuing <hi>Sheriff,</hi> doth but for reasons which himself assigns, refuse or decline the Office, than doth the naming and electing both the Sheriffs, devolve upon, and by his own acknowledgment lodg in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. And to omit other instances of this nature, I shall only mention that of the 29 of <hi>Eliz.</hi> when <hi>Richard Platt,</hi> whom my Lord Mayor had drunk unto, had by his Petition excused himself, how the Commons without the interposition of the Mayor, named and Elected <hi>Hugh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100901:22"/>Offler</hi> and <hi>Richard Saltonstall.</hi> To which I shall subjoin that late memorable President of the 32 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. when <hi>George Hock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nall</hi> being drunk to, and presented to the <hi>Commons</hi> for their Confirmation, having upon just and good grounds disengaged himself from serving, the <hi>Commons</hi> without vouchsafing my Lord Mayor the Prerogative of a new nomination, Elected and chose <hi>Slingsby Bethel</hi> and <hi>Henry Cornish.</hi> Again, is there any thing more obvious and frequent, than that when such whom my Lord Mayor hath present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have notwithstanding the honour of his Lordships no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and the reputation of being complemented and caressed into an Office by a Glass of Wine, submitted to their <hi>Fines,</hi> rather than be wheedled into the expence of three or four Thousand pounds in the <hi>Sherivalty,</hi> by pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that in such a case the Commons have been very <hi>tantely</hi> suffered to claim the naming and electing both the <hi>Sheriffs.</hi> For example, when — <hi>Charlton,</hi> whom in the 16 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. my Lord Mayor had Drunk to, yet for causes best known to himself, had the morning before the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> chose rather to Fine than to run the risk of being confirmed by the Commons to hold; the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> for the ensuing year, devolved without any dispute upon the <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> who accordingly chose <hi>John Towse</hi> and <hi>Hugh Windham.</hi> Surely these cases do to any man of sense demonstratively evince, That the Right of choosing one Sheriff does not belong unto my Lord Mayor, seeing if it did, it would indubitably belong unto him upon one mans refusal immediately to nominate another; But is not this a strange kind of Right to be lodged and vested in any which he can no where exert but in such a place, and at no time but such a day? For suppose that he to whom the Mayor drinks at the <hi>Bridg-House,</hi> should either by Death, or swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself to be less worth than 10000 <hi>l.</hi> or by some other accident, prove uncapable of serving, must not in these ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses his <hi>Lordship,</hi> for all his Prerogative of being to choose one <hi>Sheriff,</hi> be quietly contented with two such as the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100901:23"/>
               <hi>Commons</hi> think convenient to name, as well as to Elect. For my part, I never think of this pretended Prerogative of my Lord Mayor, but I think some envious Fellow that would expose the Honour of the City and Nation, was the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor and adviser of it. Nay, to proceed a little further, Even when none of these things have interven'd, yet the <hi>Commons</hi> have disputed and contested the Mayors Power in this matter, and have made him, if not plainly renounce, yet wave and abandon the insisting upon it. Thus in the 19 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. when the <hi>Mayor</hi> had nominated and presented <hi>John Fowke,</hi> the <hi>Commons</hi> refused to confirm the Election; upon which it was agreed that the Commons should for that time have the nomination of both the Sheriffs. Accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to Choice, and thinking it enough that they had as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted and vindicated their Rights, and made the Mayor su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percede his pretended Election, and having no exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the person, or dissatisfaction as to the worth and merit of <hi>John Fowke,</hi> but being meerly discontented at my Lord Mayors usurping upon their Priviledges, and attempting to thrust a Sheriff upon them, they chose the said <hi>John Fowk</hi> for one Sheriff, and <hi>James Bunce</hi> for the other. Thus also in the 26 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. when the then Mayor had drunk to <hi>William Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts,</hi> and recommended him to the <hi>Hall</hi> to be confirmed; they of the Livery did notwithstanding the high value which they had for the said Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> refuse to confirm him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this and no other account, but That the <hi>Mayor</hi> claimed it as his Prerogative to chuse one of the Sheriffs, and that he would have imposed him upon the <hi>Hall</hi> for their acceptance, as one that was both already and rightfully Elected. And we may very well remember, that after a stiff and long contest, the <hi>Commons</hi> were permitted to chuse both the Sheriffs, and my Lord Mayor was willing upon such a compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise that signified nothing to the maintaining of his pretended Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, to submit thereunto, and acquiesce in it. There are several more instances and examples of this kind, but these are enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and convince persons that have not renounced Reason, That the Lord Mayors drinking to one at the <hi>Bridg-House,</hi> does not bind the Common-Hall to confirm him for <hi>Sheriff,</hi> nor restrain them from Electing another in his room.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100901:23"/>
            <p>Now I know but one thing that can with any umbrage of Sense be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rarred unto, as a Justification of my Lord <hi>Mayors</hi> Prerogative to elect <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ually one of the two <hi>Sheriffs</hi> for <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex.</hi> And it <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an Act of <hi>Common-Council</hi> in the 7th. of the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hich among other-things, <hi>It is enacted, ordained, and established by the Lord</hi> Mayor <hi>and</hi> Aldermen, <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>in Common Council assembled; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That from thenceforth for ever, the day as well for Confirmation <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Allowance of such persons as hereafter shall be chosen and elected by <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Lord</hi> Mayor <hi>of this City for the time being, to be Sheriffs of the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d City and County of Middlesex; as also for the Choice and Election <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> such other persons as by the Lord</hi> Mayo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Aldermen, <hi>and</hi> Commons <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>all be chosen to be</hi> Sheriffs <hi>of the said City and County of Middlesex, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>all be yearly held on the</hi> 24. <hi>day of</hi> June. To which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> briefly reply two <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ings, whereof the first is, That if the meaning of this <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Common Council</hi> be, what the Advocates for my Lord <hi>Mayors</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ogative contend for; namely, that the right of Electing one <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ff</hi> is in him, and that the <hi>Commons</hi> are tamely to acquiesce in, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>plicitely to consent to the choice which he is alledged to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>say, If this be the meaning of the <hi>Act,</hi> it is directly against all their Charters which have been ratified by so many Acts of Farlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; therefore <hi>ipso facto</hi> void and null. For tho' my Lord Mayo, the Court of Aldermen, and Commons in Common Council assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, may make Laws agreeable to the Charter; yet they can make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one that directly gainsay and overthrow it. And if an Act of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ament may be null in it self, and those punished that presume to Act upon it when it is against those Rights which we enjoy by the Common Law of the Land; surely an Act of Common Council may also be null, if it be against those Liberties which belong unto the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens by Charter and Prescription. And if an Act of Parliament upon the Authority whereof <hi>Dudley</hi> and <hi>Empson</hi> acted, would not preserve them from being hang'd, because 'twas against the Common Rights of <hi>English</hi> men: it is very likely that an Act of <hi>Common-Council</hi> will not secure others from being called to an account, if they trample upon the legal Priviledges and Jurisdictions of the City. And I remember that the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled 2. <hi>May</hi> 1628. did judge and declare upon the Complaint of one <hi>Legate,</hi> a certain Act of the <hi>Common Council</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to be null in it self, and all Proceedings upon it to be unjust and illegal. And in the 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. where upon a frustration of the Election of <hi>Sheriffs</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100901:24"/>on <hi>Midsummer-day</hi> because of the <hi>Commons</hi> refusing to confirm him whom Sir <hi>Edward Wright</hi> the then Lord <hi>Major</hi> had named, the whole matter, was brought before the Lords assembled in Parliament; I remember how on the hearing of both Parties, <hi>Their Lordships did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That the Commonalty should forthwith proceed to the nomination and Election of both Sheriffs for the year ensuing.</hi> Though I do confess, that in the said Order, they do not preclude the <hi>Mayors</hi> from disputing their Prerogative in a legal and fair way, if they have any. And forasmuch as most of the Cases I mentioned before, wherein the <hi>Mayors</hi> waved and abandoned the insisting upon any Prerogative or Right in this matter, have fallen out since the said <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Common-Council</hi> was made; this plainly testifies and shows, that themselves judged that <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Common-Council</hi> too weak and incompetent to support and justifie their Claim of imposing a <hi>Sheriff</hi> upon, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing one unto the City.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I say, that the words in the said Act of Common-Council, which provide that the <hi>Commons are on such a day to confirm and allow him whom the Mayor hath elected,</hi> do plainly declare, That they have power not to allow, or confirm him? For what sense is there, to say, They are to allow and confirm, if they have not the liberty and priviledg to disallow, and refuse to confirm? And what becomes of the <hi>libera Electio vicecomitum,</hi> that is to be granted to the <hi>Barons</hi> or Freemen of <hi>London</hi> by so many <hi>Charters,</hi> and provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for by the City Laws, if the <hi>Commons</hi> be bound to submit to the Person that the <hi>Mayor</hi> does name? This were to betray you into Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very by the plausible Terms of Liberty, Priviledg, and Power, and to cheat you of your Rights by fair, but insignificant and fallacious words. Rouz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up your selves then to a modest, peaceable and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screet Consideration of your Duties. You may easily know where your In erest lyes and what is designed by the warmth and Indefatigableness of your E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emies. The business relating to the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the forfeiture of your Charter, is before the Judges, who I suppose will do you Justice and Right, and remember that there is no president that ever this great and honourable <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the Kingdom was ever wholly <hi>disfranchised,</hi> or reduced into a <hi>Village,</hi> since it was first a <hi>Corporation.</hi> And had that at any time been, they could never since have claimed those Priviledges and Jurisdictions which they held and enjoyed by ancient <hi>Prescription.</hi> For if <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription</hi> be once extinguished, no Princes Grant afterwards, or <hi>Writ</hi> of <hi>Restitution</hi> can revive it. 'Tis true, there have sometimes been sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zures
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100901:24"/>of the City Rights; but I dare boldly say, That the City was never to this day <hi>discorporate;</hi> only their Priviledges were taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of some of their Kings, till they had made some little Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and reconciled themselves by some petty Gifts to their angry and incensed Princes. Yea, the last seizure of the City Priviledges which was in <hi>Rich</hi> 2's. time above 290 years ago, was not upon a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or <hi>Verdict</hi> of the Judges of the <hi>Iter's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Walsing. R.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 348.</note> or of the Courts at Law, but meerly an Act of the Will and Pleasure of that King, with and upon the advice of some <hi>Lords</hi> whom he had called together and consulted in that affair, And I am almost ready to think, that if the Lords the <hi>Judges</hi> should annul and give away the <hi>Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> of the City upon the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> brought lately against it, that then they may ere long find another served against the House of Commons, as being according to Dr. <hi>Brady</hi> of a much later stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having had its first beginning only in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3's. time; (and that, if you will believe him, meerly upon Rebellion), and being voiced by many to have behaved themselves for some years past unmannerly to his Majesty, presumptuously towards his Ministers, and arbitrarily towards divers of those who stile themselves his Majesties only Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects. But Gentlemen Citizens! tho' the matter of the <hi>Quo. Warranto</hi> doth not lye before you, yet the preserving your ancient and legal Right of chusing both the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> is wholly in your own hands, and under your power, and none can strip or deprive you of it, unless your selves renounce and abandon it. And let me only tell you, That if you acknowledg a Prerogative in the <hi>Mayor</hi> to chuse ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually one <hi>Sheriff,</hi> it is more than probable, that your <hi>Mayors</hi> may in process of time challenge and usurp the Election of both. For the Freemen have the same Right and Authority <hi>annually</hi> to chuse <hi>two,</hi> which they have to chuse one; and if they suffer themselves to be wheedled or threatned out of the first, it will be a good encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for the <hi>Mayors</hi> to wrest the second from them likewise. For it is not by reason of any apprehension or fear of Danger unto themselves from the Gentlemen that are thought upon by others for <hi>Sheriffs</hi> against the ensuing year, that they make all this Clamour, Contest and Bustle, but it is from a hope and belief to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress and ruine you, if they can but obtain a <hi>Sheriff</hi> of their own Kidney and Figure. Have any of them suffered by means of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice or Partiality of the Gentlemen who have executed that Office these two last years? Nay, have not some of them escap'd what by the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100901:25"/>Law they deserved to undergo? Whence then is all this earnestne<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to impose a <hi>Sheriff</hi> upon you, contrary to all Right and Equity, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the very <hi>Tenor</hi> of your. Charters, but in subserviency to some De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sign they have projected and laid against your Persons and Estates<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Dare you judge your selves worthy of those Priviledges and Jur<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dictions which the Kings of <hi>England</hi> bestow'd upon your Ancestor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and which his present Majesty hath confirmed unto you; if by deserting and abandoning the defence of them, you judg them only fit to be given up and sacrificed to the humour and will of a perso<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that hath nothing to distinguish him from many of your selves, bu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the sitting in a <hi>Chair</hi> wherein you placed him, and which he mu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> surrender to another in a few Months? Think what your posterity will say of you, when they are upbraided with the Folly and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileness of their Fathers, who lost more from them in a lame and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequious parting with the Rights and Priviledges of Citizens, than all the Parchment Titles and Wealth which you can convey un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, do bear proportion unto. Nay will not the <hi>Ghosts</hi> of you Fore-fathers, when they shall see their Children destroy'd by pac<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Juries, upbraid you as a degenerate Offspring, and drive away you<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Base and timorous Senses from a <hi>participation</hi> in that happiness which their own zeal for, and Conformity unto the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion, with their fidelity for the Interests of Mankind and the Rights o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> this Noble City, prepared and adapted them for? And should you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert the asserting your Rights at such a juncture as this, will not your Guilt make you a terror to your selves, and your slavish Folly and Baseness fill you with shame before others? Do you not think what will become of your Religion and Laws, should God take away his Majesty? And will not the Courses that many within your own walls are pursuing, sacilitate and enable your Adversaries to effect it? I hope you will pardon this Transport; for one cannot show himself affected as he ought for so good a Cause, without being picquant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a sort of men that have nothing to distinguish them from <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Baboons,</hi> but that they have learned to talk; for their Action<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are infinitely more <hi>indecorous,</hi> unreasonable, and silly. For my self<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> I love both <hi>English</hi> Liberty and the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion; and if<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> must be a Slave, I will chuse rather to be one in <hi>Turkey,</hi> than <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> Or if I must exchange my Religion, I will sooner worship the <hi>Sun,</hi> than the <hi>Pairing</hi> of St. <hi>Frances Toes,</hi> or the <hi>Snot</hi> and <hi>Snivel</hi> of <hi>Loyala's Nose.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Si mundus vult decipi decipiatur.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>